If you're like the majority of
Americans, the street in front of your
house probably looks something like
this. Wide with parking on both sides,
driveways, front yards, houses. All
pretty standard, really. But I'm here to
tell you that they could be better. Now,
I know it's hard to imagine better when
you're surrounded by the status quo, but
there are lots of ways to design a
neighborhood street. You only need to
take a look over at Europe for proof.
You can have shared streets that
prioritize pedestrians and cyclists to
make cars feel like uninvited guests. In
the Netherlands, they're called a
wounderf. In Britain, they're called a
home zone. Even their more normal local
streets are often narrower than ours.
These streets come from a philosophy
that emphasizes the safety and comfort
of residents over the convenience of
speeding down the street to get to your
driveway. Parents can let their kids
play knowing they won't get mowed down
the second they step off the curb.
That's real freedom right there. Now, I
know what you're thinking. Europeans
don't have wide streets because they
don't drive as much as we do. Well, the
road designs I just showed you don't
change capacity all that much. And
contrary to popular belief, Europeans do
own cars and they do drive them. In
Italy, on average, nearly 75% of the
distance traveled per day is done by
car. It's nearly 70% in Germany. In bike
crazy Netherlands, it's 62%. These
countries do still plan for cars as the
dominant mode of transportation. I
actually did a whole video about whether
US cities can build narrow European
streets. Go check it out if you like.
So, I think European streets can provide
a useful template for streets here in
the United States, but I get it.
European street planning is a hard cell
here in the United States and we like
our curbs, gutters, sidewalks, and
separated travel lanes. This video then
is all about how to design streets
according to the US vernacular. Can we
add in something a little bit European,
a little bit narrower while still
getting past the planning commission? I
think the answer is yes, and we'll show
you after the bike bell.
[bell]
Let's set the stage. What is a
neighborhood street supposed to do
exactly? The answer might seem obvious
because you're used to seeing one in
your everyday life. But how does it
actually function? Neighborhood streets
exist to provide access. All the houses
along that street need that street to
get to the rest of the city via the road
network. There are three tiers to the
road network in US cities. It's a street
hierarchy. Local streets are at one end.
I've been calling them neighborhood
streets, but local streets is the
official engineering term. I'll use
those two terms interchangeably in this
video. Local streets offer the lowest
speeds but the greatest access. It's
anticipated that these streets would be
lined with driveways and people coming
in and out at regular intervals. On the
other side of the spectrum, arterial
streets allow for high speeds and
relatively few driveways or access
points. They're about moving traffic
fast long distances. Collector streets
are somewhere in the middle. So, the
goal of the local street is to ensure
that all the homes along it have access
and to ensure traffic speeds and volumes
are relatively low. They're designed to
easily handle 1,000 to 2,000 vehicles
per day. You'll notice that this bit
about the road network is very car
oriented and that's because it is. It
was designed around the car first here
in the United States. This is not good
and particularly bad on local streets
where you see a great many of people
walking. People walking their dog or
walking off a heavy dinner. Kids ride
bikes or scooters, but local streets
aren't really designed for that group of
people. In lots of neighborhoods,
sidewalks don't even exist at all.
>> Now, I can't find any statistics for the
number of streets without sidewalks. I
wish I could. I actually grew up on a
street without a sidewalk. The
explanation I got for why was that the
local developers told the city council
that sidewalks cost too much. So now the
city doesn't require them. I've also
heard that no sidewalks look more rural
and bucallic, you know, less urban. And
suburbanites want that because they're
in the suburbs because they don't want
to be in the city. And in some places
where there are sidewalks, they're right
up against the curb. And that's just not
ideal. Nobody wants to be walking when
their cars zooming right by you. It's
just not very comfortable. Now that we
know what a local street is supposed to
do, let's start designing. The first
thing we need to do is figure out how
big of a canvas we have to work with.
That canvas is called the right of way.
It's the area the local government owns
and controls. Everything else is private
property. Here in the United States,
local streets usually have a right of
way of about 50 to 60 ft. Collector
streets are about 60 to 80 ft wide.
Arterials can go from 60 to 120 ft wide
or more. Let's choose the narrowest
common right of way for our local
street, 50 ft. Why should we want our
right of way to be narrow? Well, small
right ofway means less area for a local
government to maintain. It keeps costs
and therefore taxes lower. It also means
that real estate developers have more
area to sell to homeowners and make
money. It's a win-win.
>> Okay, so now that we have our canvas, we
can start painting it with our
collection of lanes, lines, and other
design elements. I'll be using
streetmix.net for this. I highly
recommend this tool for anyone who wants
to redesign a street. It's just simple
drag and drop. You can set your right of
way, 50 ft in this case, and then start
assembling. What do we put in this 50
ft? We can't just put in rows for cars
and call it a day. We could use the
design philosophy called complete
streets. Complete streets was a movement
that came about around 25 years ago.
Reformers saw that US streets were
incomplete, meaning that they only
served one mode reliably, the car. They
wanted to design streets for everybody.
Here's a snippet from their mission
statement on the Smart Growth America
website, home to the Complete Streets
Coalition. It says, "Complete streets
are universal. They're designed for
everyone. Pedestrians, cyclists,
drivers, and public transit users of all
ages and abilities. You might already
notice the challenge of this approach on
a local street. Does the quiet street in
front of my house need to accommodate
transit users like buses? That's where
the concept of contextsensitive
solutions comes in. It sort of refineses
the complete street idea by recommending
that planners consider the immediate
context of the street. If there will
never be bus service on our neighborhood
street, then no bus lane is necessary.
We do need to have a street wide enough
to allow emergency vehicles, though. You
want a fire truck or ambulance to make
it to your house. The most common
minimum width you'll see to allow for
emergency vehicles is 20 ft. It's just
harder to design a modern street
narrower than that. Another context
consideration here is parking. How much
parking does a residential neighborhood
like this need? Well, uh there are
studies out on this. I even wrote a
couple of them and the answer is pretty
clear. There's enough storage capacity
off streetet for all those cars. You
don't really need a lot of on street
parking.
>> If you include garages, there's way more
than enough. But I know that if you live
in California like me, your garage
stores everything but cars. I still miss
my Midwestern basement. I know that
while driveways can often store all
cars, lots of people prefer not to stack
them up in the driveway and instead like
to park one of their cars on the street.
So, strictly speaking, on street parking
is a nice to have and not a need to
have. But if you're a diehard on street
parker, I have some good news. There's
an argument to be made for including on
street parking. And that's not all about
uh the capacity of the street and all
that. It's because on street parking
actually narrows the perceived width of
the street. And when streets are
narrower, people drive slower. And when
people drive slower, it's safer. They're
safer because if a slow car hits you,
you'll probably dust yourself off and
end up with some bumps or bruises, maybe
a broken bone. If a car hits you going
45 miles an hour, your surviving that
crash is a coin flip. Slower is
definitely better. Slower also makes it
easier to see and avoid people before
you hit them. This is critical on a
local street because there are lots of
people, particularly kids, running
around. When you're driving fast, your
field of vision narrows to what's right
in front of you. Your brain just can't
process a wider field of view or your
peripheral vision. That's why people say
that someone jumped out in front of them
when they hit a pedestrian. No
pedestrian is jumping out in front of a
car. It just seemed like that to the
driver because their field of view was
so narrow. Objects like parked cars can
create obstacles that slow traffic and
help drivers see all potential hazards.
That's why for my money, the best local
street has some on street parking.
>> Okay, so that's enough preamble. Let me
show you the design right now.
>> It's 22 feet wide curb to curb. 22 ft is
wide enough for parking on one side of
the street and two lanes of traffic if
the cars negotiate carefully around the
parked cars. This is called queuing, and
it further slows down traffic. Now, for
most trips, drivers won't have to do
this. With only 1,000 cars per day, it's
just not super likely that you'll see
another car. But with all of the
driveways, there should be enough space
between parked cars for the drivers to
do a little dance and decide who goes
through first. The rest of the design is
pretty straightforward. The planted
buffer is 7 ft wide, wide enough for a
goodiz street tree. Street trees are so
important that I did a whole video on
them. You can go check it out here. The
gist is this. Street trees clean the
local air, improving air quality. They
can also help with that visual friction
that the parked cars provide further
slowing traffic. Because our street is
so narrow, the trees, when fully grown,
will create a canopy over the street.
This can shade the pavement, reducing
the urban heat island effect. It also
makes the street super beautiful and
charming, which is just great. Studies
have also shown that shade and trees are
unevenly distributed in our cities,
meaning that lowincome residents don't
get that benefit of shade as often as
upper income residents. This design that
I'm proposing, if used everywhere, would
eliminate that difference. And in a
rapidly warming world, this seems really
critical and timely. The final piece of
this is the sidewalks. 5 feet is kind of
the standard, though I've seen stingier
neighborhoods with just four feet. My
recommendation is six feet. Just as a
note, usually the right of way of a
street extends a foot past the sidewalk
into the front yard. That means you
might not actually own every foot of
your yard. That's also why our sidewalk
isn't 7 ft. 7 ft is definitely better
because it's even easier for two people
to walk next to each other and talk, but
six isn't half bad. Now, this is not a
complete street. There are no bike
lanes. A street like this doesn't really
need them. The traffic is so slow that
cycling is generally considered safe.
And with traffic volume so low, a
cyclist is unlikely to encounter a car
in the first place. Bikes are also so
narrow that they should pass a car right
next to a park car no problem. And
there's just enough space to navigate
fine. An open driving lane of 15 ft is
also plenty wide for garbage trucks,
emergency vehicles, and other large
vehicles. The great thing about this
design is that it's narrow enough to
encourage slow speeds without the need
for speed humps, chicanees, or other
artificial means of slowing down cars.
These can be useful on existing streets
designed too wide in the first place,
but we don't need them on this perfect
street. Now, if you think that this
design is new or radical, I can assure
you that it is not. My proposal is a
synthesis of two ideas put forth in the
state of Oregon's neighborhood street
design guidelines from the year 2000.
These ideas have been floating around
for longer than a lot of my audience has
been alive. Speaking of things that have
been around for a long time, Tom Scott
made videos every single week for 10
straight years. Then he took a
muchneeded break, but now he's back. And
previously his channel was on things
like geography, history, science, and
more. And now he's touring England and
visiting every single county. Uh I'm so
excited that he's doing this. I'm so
happy he's back. He's on my Pantheon.
He's on my Mount Rushmore for great
YouTube creators. Uh I look up to his
channel. I've had the chance to meet Tom
and he's fantastic. A guy worth cheering
for and I'm so happy he's making videos
again. And you can check out those
videos where he visits every county in
England over on Nebula. Nebula is a
creatorowned streaming video service
where Tom Scott and I post our videos
early and adree. We've actually got a
ton of urbanism content over on Nebula
2. We've got channels like Not Just
Bikes, City Nerd, Downey Live, Wendover
Productions, and my channel too. I even
have exclusive Nebula original series
over there called Great Cities, which
chronicles the most important pieces of
infrastructure in the world's greatest
cities. you will never be bored. Another
great thing about Nebula is that many of
us, including me, post our YouTube
content to Nebula early. I actually post
my videos one full video ahead. That
means if you see a New City, beautiful
video on YouTube, the next one is
already up on Nebula. I even have a
Nebulaon Discord server where you can
chat about videos long before YouTube
commenters. Those videos also don't have
any YouTube ads. Nebula is completely
adfree. Now, you can get all of this for
a surprisingly affordable price. And
when you sign up at my link, nebula.tv/
TV/ city beautiful. You'll get 50% off
an annual subscription. My channel will
even get a portion of that subscription
fee as long as you stay subscribed. So,
it's one of the best ways to support me
and this channel. Nebula is also
offering lifetime memberships for people
who want to go above and beyond in their
love and support of the channel and
platform. I think it's great that we
have a couple of different ways of
allowing people to show their support.
So go click on the link and start
exploring England with Tom Scott early
and ad free.